<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Serverless on Gareth's Engineering Blog</title><link>https://gazsecops.github.io/tags/serverless/</link><description>Recent content in Serverless on Gareth's Engineering Blog</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-gb</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 18:56:28 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gazsecops.github.io/tags/serverless/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Azure Logic Apps Security: A Guide for Cyber Security Consultants</title><link>https://gazsecops.github.io/posts/azure-logic-apps-security-guide/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 12:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gazsecops.github.io/posts/azure-logic-apps-security-guide/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Azure Logic Apps are everywhere in modern cloud architectures. They&amp;rsquo;re the glue between services - orchestrating workflows, connecting APIs, moving data between systems. But from a security perspective, they&amp;rsquo;re also potential attack surfaces if configured poorly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="pullquote"&gt;
"Your job as a consultant isn't to tick boxes - it's to understand the architecture, identify the risks, and provide actionable recommendations. Security isn't a checklist. It's understanding the system and identifying where it can be broken."
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This guide is for cyber security consultants assessing environments that use Azure Logic Apps. It covers the architecture, key configuration areas that matter for security, threat modeling, and common pitfalls to look out for. It&amp;rsquo;s about understanding what&amp;rsquo;s configurable, what the threats are, and where things typically go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logic Apps are interesting from a security perspective because they sit at the intersection of multiple services. They&amp;rsquo;re serverless (no infrastructure to manage), highly configurable (1000+ connectors), and often have significant permissions (managed identities with broad access). When misconfigured, they become pivot points for lateral movement, data exfiltration, or supply chain attacks. They&amp;rsquo;re also easy to overlook in security assessments because they&amp;rsquo;re &amp;ldquo;just workflow automation&amp;rdquo; - until you realize they have Contributor access to your entire subscription.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>